Guide to the Jack Kerouac Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Jack Kerouac Papers
1945-1971.
Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.
.5 linear ft. (1 document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0708
4078982
Novelist and member of the Beat Generation. The collection includes a small amount of correspondence, manuscript material and ephemera by and relating to Jack Kerouac.
Biographical Note
Jack Kerouac, born Jean-Louis Lebris de Kerouac, was born in 1922 in Lowell, Massachusetts to French Canadian parents. Kerouac spent much of his youth engaged in sports and other physical activities. His athletic prowess earned him a football scholarship to Columbia University where he matriculated in 1940, but he left Columbia in the Fall of 1941 after sustaining an injury that left him unable to play football.
Upon leaving the University Kerouac joined the Merchant Marine and later the US Navy, but retained close ties to members of the Columbia community. He lived on Manhattan's Upper West Side with his girlfriend, later first wife, Barnard student Edie Parker and her friend Joan Vollmer. It was through Parker that Kerouac met Columbia students Allen Ginsberg and Lucien Carr and their friends William Burroughs and Herbert Huncke. This group of friends and writers which would later form the nucleus of the Beat Generation, was the inspiration for much of Kerouac's work.
Kerouac married Edie Parker in 1944 and moved with her to her home in Grosse Pointe, Michigan, but their marriage lasted less than a year. Upon the annulment of the marriage, Kerouac returned to New York and his bohemian friends and began to write the novel which would become The Town and the City-- this novel, Kerouac's first, was published in 1950 to mild acclaim.
Kerouac's next novel, On the Road proved to be much more commercially and critically successful. This novel, published in 1957 documents a trip Kerouac took across the US and Northern Mexico with Neal Cassady. This fictionalized account of Kerouac and his friends introduced the beats to America solidified the image of the beatnik with his interest in sexual freedom, jazz, and drug use in the popular imagination.
Though Kerouac's goal had long been to be a writer, the success of On the Road never sat entirely well with its author. Kerouac continued to write his thinly veiled autobiographical novels chronicling his bohemian, literary circle of friends, but in his personal life he began to pull away from the public eye and distance himself from his Beat Generation associated. He moved to Northport, Long Island to care for his aging parents and growing more personally and politically conservative.
Kerouac died of cirrhosis of the liver in 1969.
Scope and Content
This is a collection of material related to Jack Kerouac pulled together from various sources and donors. It includes correspondence and ephemera as well as manuscripts of small poems and prose fragments and proofs of Desolation Angels and Tristessa.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in II series:
I. Correspondence, 1945-1971
II. Manuscripts and Miscellaneous, 1960-1956, undated
Subjects
Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; Lucey, Ellen.; Louisiana--Description and travel.; Mexico--Description and travel.; Morocco--Description and travel.; Beat generation.; Bohemianism--United States.; American literature--20th century.; Portraits.; Authors, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1970 M-70 Lucey, Ellen Gift
Alternate Formats
William Burroughs letters available on microfilm.
Related Material-- At Columbia
William S. Burroughs Papers Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Columbia University
Related Material-- Other Repositories
Jack Kerouac Papers, 1920-1977, bulk (1935-1969). Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature New York Public Library
- Series I: Correspondence, 1945-1971
  This series consists of letters sent to Kerouac by friends and associates, as well as letters sent by Kerouac to fans and admirers. This series also consists of a few letters about the author sent to and from Kerouac’s family and acquaintances. These include 35 letters of William Burroughs to Jack Kerouac which deal with his daily life and thoughts in Louisiana, Mexico, and Morocco, with his writings and those of Kerouac, and with their mutual friends including Allen Ginsberg. Several examples of Burroughs' experimental prose are included.
  - Arrabel, Fernando to Kerouac, 1968 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burroughs, William to Allen Ginsberg, 1959 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Burroughs, William to Kerouac
    - 1945 July - 1950 December (14 letters) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1951- 1952 April (7 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1945 April- 1955 June (11 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1957, 1962 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Giroux, Robert to Ellen Lucey, 1952 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kerouac, Jack
    - to Elbert Lenrow, 1949 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - to Ellen Lucey, 1951, 1961 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kerouac, Stella Sampas (Mrs. Jack) to Ellen Lucey, 1969-1971 (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lax, Robert to Ellen Lucey, 1959-1971 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - O'Neill, John H. to Kerouac, 1950 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Manuscripts and Miscellaneous, 1960-1965 and undated
  This series consists of a small number of manuscripts of Kerouac’s poetry and prose fragments as well as proofs of two of Kerouac's novels, Desolation Angels and Tristessa. This series also includes clippings and reviews and some of Kerouac's published work. It includes Big Table 1 which contains the first installment of Kerouac's "Old Angel Midnight" as well as Evergreen Review no.33 which contains the second installment. There is also a memorial portrait of Kerouac by Robert LaVigne
  - Desolation Angels- Uncorrected Proof, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "If onions made the eye more weep…" (includes lines later incorporated into "Pull My Daisy") (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "My eagle…" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "In the rainy night the bat…" (untitled prose fragment) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tristessa- advance proof, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings and Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Posters
    - Poster for Jack Kerouac: A Chicken-Essay by Victor Levy-Beaulieu (Shelf Oversize)
    - Photo Poster of Kerouac by Antonio A. Rubino (Shelf Oversize)
    - Poster for "On the Road: The Jack Kerouac Conference," 1982 (Shelf Oversize)